Preliminary Inventory to the Revolution and The Development of International Relations Project Records, 1948-1952
Hoover Institution Archives
Revolution and the Development of International Relations Project Records,
1948-1952
XX513
Revolution and the Development of International Relations Project
72 manuscript boxes, 16 card file boxes. (32.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoranda, correspondence, data sheets, and printed matter, relating to the comparative study of social, political, and economic development in various countries during the twentieth century, and especially to the comparative study of political and military elites in various countries.
Administrative Information
Access
Boxes 87-88 (personnel files) closed indefinitely.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Armed Forces--Political activity.; Economic development.; Elite (Social sciences); International relations.; Social change
Container List
- American publishers (Box 1)
- RADIR correspondence
  - A-F, 1951-1952
  - G-M, 1951-1952
  - N-S, 1951-1952
  - T-Z, 1951-1952
- Publications
  - Workbook, 1948
  - Schedule and general instructions
  - Clippings and reviews
  - Letters of acknowledgement, thanks and possible quotes
  - Letters to authors and letters of commission
  - Mailing lists; promotion (Box 2)
  - Notification list and promises to send
  - Review list and correspondence
  - Negotiations with press
- Clipping collection project
- Committee on Communication (Chicago)
- Confidential
- Content analysis, the Elite Symbol Study
- Content analysis, Newspaper Study
- Content analysis, ORO project with SRI
- Foundation Nacionale des Sciences Politiques correspondence with Meynand
- Liaison (other projects) (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
- Public education projects, general (Box 4)
- Public education projects, Conferences
- Public education projects, Personal
- Publicity, releases, clippings
- RADIR New York meeting
- Rand Corporation
- Reports to Carnegie Institute
- Special projects
- Speakers
- Speeches
- Staff meetings
- Area Studies (Box 5)
  - China
  - Great Britain
  - Greece
  - Latin America
  - Philippines and Southeast Asia
  - Poland
  - Soviet Union
  - Spain
  - Turkey
  - Yugoslavia
  - Italy
- Conference, Carr
- Conference, Attendance, January 1948
- Conference, General report and Comments, January 1948
- Conference, Sessions (Box 6)
- Conference, H. Laswell, January 27-28, 1948
- Conference, RADIR, July 5-9, 1948
- Conference, Talbot, May 1, 1948
- CER Country studies, workbook, 1948
- CER Country studies, United States
- CER Country studies, U.S.S.R.
- Democracy, elites
- Democracy, voting
- Democracy, Symbol and myth
- Preliminary memoranda, documents 1 and 2
- Memoranda (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
  - Baran, July 1948
  - Beukema, June 1948
  - Brookings, Soviet Union in World Affairs (first papers)
  - Brookings, Soviet Union in World Affairs (copy and comments)
  - Brooking seminar, 1948
  - Fairbank, June 1948
  - Ford proposal
  - Ford proposal, adult education
  - Ford proposal, areas proposal
  - Goldschmidt
  - Keesing
  - Kirk, June 1948
  - Lerner
  - Lasswell, June 1948 (Box 8)
  - Newmann, July 1948
  - Padover, July-August 1948
  - Rothwell, August 1948
  - World Politics, Rothwell
  - Siegel, June-August 1948
  - Staley, 1948
- Problem papers
  - Czech Revolution
  - Social Composition of German Parties
  - Aims of German Foreign Policy, 1871-1939
  - Decline of Great Britain's Power position
  - Baran East-West Trade
  - Outline on Study of Technology
  - Soviet foreign Policy
  - Technological trends in Great Britain, 1890-1946
  - General
- Elite Studies (Box 9)
  - American Executive
  - French Executive
  - Great Britain
  - International elite
  - Malayan elite
  - Thailand elite
  - Nazi elite
  - United States (Box 10)
- International Political Warfare Seminar
- Psychological Warfare Reader
- Psychological Warfare Seminar II
- Propaganda Seminar, 1949-1950.
- Graduate Seminar Social Science
- M. Allport, correspondence
- O. Gargill, correspondence
- Unpaid invoices
- D. Lerner's Eastern trip, 1948
- Libraries
- Unpaid book bills
- Paid book bills
- Translations and extractions
- Berliner Zeitung excerpts, May 22, 1945, March 10, 1946
- Tagessiegel, excerpts January 1948
- Newspaper Clippings
- Phase II survey (Box 11)
- Turkish audiences
- D. Lerner's letters for permission, Propaganda in War and Crisis
- D. Lerner book reviews
- Hoover series M-L (Gershik-Lerner)
- European trips, 1946-1948 and D. Lerner correspondence with H. Fisher
- The American Soldier
- I. Pool correspondence
- H. Laswell correspondence
- Sykwar, correspondence
- A lasting peace, for people's democracy (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous reprints
- British Public Opinion surveys
- Dutch Public Opinion (Box 13)
- Twentieth of July conspiracy
- Organ for European Economic Cooperation
- Russian Research Center
- S. Tyrol reports
- Das Bucherblatt
- Chinese Democratic Constitutional Party
- Der Gegen-Angriff, Antifaschistische
- The Road away from Revolution, Woodrow Wilson
- Survey of Current Business Review, February 1948
- Mass Observation Bulletin
- Draft of Policy Sciences
- Policy Sciences in the United States, by Laswell and Lerner (Box 14)
  (working papers)
- Politburo data
- RADIR workbook, 1948
- D. Lerner correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 15)
- Elite target analysis, by Alfred De Grazia
- Elite study notes, H. Fisher
- Conclusions and recommendations (Box 16)
- Quincy Wright - Easton Rothwell, correspondence, 1951
- RADIR Country-Area Studies, 1948
- Japan in the World Community, by N. Ike, 1950
- RADIR research - work completed, functional studies, Country studies
- RADIR papers (working collection)
- 13th Conference on Science, Philosophy and Religion
- R. Adloff, notes and miscellaneous
- RADIR project, work completed or in progress
- Consultants (Box 17)
- Department of Army
- Department of State
- Hum RRO
- Hum RRO - Administration
- Hum RRO - Precontract negotiations
- Paul Katona
- Lerner - Melite
- Lerner - personal
- Library of Congress
- M. Loventhal
- D. McNown
- Melite correspondence
  - A-F
  - G-M
  - N-S
  - T-Z
- Miscellaneous memorandums
- Gerald Popiel
- Nicholas Poppe
- Radio Free Europe
- Research Assistants
- G. Schueller - Melite
- G. Schueller, Personal
- G. Schueller correspondence, 1947-1952
- S. Yakobson
- Sociological Society meeting, 1953, papers
- Soviet Melite, correspondence
- Soviet Israelite data
- Soviet Scientists reports
- Melite questionnaire, correspondence
- Melite Extension correspondence
- Basic research proposals
- Stanford Business Office, memos.
- Consultants authorization to use names in Melite reports
- IBM, correspondence
- Public negotiations
- Public negotiations request for clearance
- Satellite Military Elite, correspondence
- Administration (Box 18)
  - Applications - Melite
  - Budget - Melite
  - IBM (San Jose) Job agreement
  - Interlibrary loan requests
  - Progress reports - Melite
  - Requisitions - consultants
  - Requisitions, documents
  - Requisitions, microfilm
  - Requisitions, supplies
  - Basic research proposals
  - Stencils
  - Telegrams
  - Monthly time sheets
  - Travel vouchers
  - Research assistants' reports
- Summary and recommendations, by I. Pool
- China, draft by Pool
- Czechoslovakia, draft by Pool
- Hungary
- Poland (Box 19)
- Reports, distribution list
- Summary draft
- Reports for society meeting, Berkeley
- Soviet Military Elite, by Laswell and Schueller
  (ms. draft of book)
- Soviet Military Elite, by Laswell and Schueller (Box 20)
- Biographical sketches of Soviet Marshals
- Soviet Israelite, appendix
- Soviet Scientific Elite, by Alexander Vucinich (ms. for book)
- Soviet Scientific Elite (Box 21)
- Academy of Sciences, Poppe's report
- Academy of Sciences, Poppe's report, 1st draft
- Conclusions and recommendations, D. Lerner
- Lerner report cover letter
- Country Studies - Melite (Box 22)
  - Albania
  - Bulgaria
  - Burma
  - China
  - Czechoslovakia
  - Egypt
  - Hungary
  - India
  - Japan (Box 23)
  - Pakistan
  - Poland
  - Poland (Box 24)
  - Rumania
  - Spain
  - Sweden
  - Turkey
  - USSR (Box 25)
  - United States
  - Yugoslavia
  - Statistics, misc.
- Comparative Military Elite Data Sheets by countries alphabetically organized (Box 26)
  - Bulgaria
  - China
    - Chen-ping
    - Su-Yu - Tse Yun (Box 27)
    - Nationalists
      - Chang - Hsu
      - Hu-Yuan (Box 28)
    - Nationalists and Communists combined
      - Chen-Chang - Chien Cheng
      - Kai M Cheng - Shun-Chu-ho (Box 29)
      - Cheng-Tsao h[UNK]u - Tse-Yun (Box 30)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - Bacilek - Boeck
    - Braun-Husarek (Box 31)
    - Imro - Krdlacek (Box 32)
    - Langer - Satorie (Box 33)
    - Sindelar - Zeman (Box 34)
  - Hungary (Box 35)
    - Abt - Czeydner
    - Dallos - Haroy (Box 36)
    - Hazi - Kutg (Box 37)
    - Lakatos - Muennich (Box 38)
    - Nady - Subrics (Box 39)
    - Szabo - Zaray (Box 40)
  - India and Pakistan (Box 41)
    - A - Z
  - Japan (Box 42)
    - Abe - Ichioka
    - Ichise - Minami (Box 43)
    - Mita - Skigeru (Box 44)
    - Shioda - Tsukada (Box 45)
    - Uchiyama - Yoshihara (Box 46)
  - Poland (Box 47)
    - Abraham - Kleeberg
    - Knoll-Kownacki - Piskor (Box 48)
    - Pitsudski - Zwierzchowski (Box 49)
  - Rumania (Box 50)
    - Aldea - Dumitrescu
    - Eftimiu - Rusescu (Box 51)
    - Salajan - Zuiedeneck (Box 52)
  - Spain
    - Abarzusa - Cuerda
    - Davila - Rodriguez (Box 53)
    - Romero - Villalba (Box 54)
  - Sweden (Box 55)
  - U.S.S.R. (Box 56)
    - Abrikosov - Ermolaev
    - Favorskii - Koslovskii (Box 57)
    - Krachkovskii - Prasolov (Box 58)
    - Rahimov - Zemin (Box 59)
- Statistical tables by countries (Box 60)
  - India
  - Japan
  - Spain
  - Sweden
  - U.S.S.R. with list of officers, and source material
- International Elites notes, by Richard Fisher (Box 61-62)
- RADIR - Symbols, notes, cards, charts, working papers and Schueller notes (Box 63-69)
- Project report. "The Soviet Union in World Affairs: 1948" (Box 70)
- Miscellany
- Bibliographic material in card form, 16 boxes at end of collection (Box 71-86)